[Music]
hi again Mark here from talkingbass.net
this lesson I'll be covering one of the
most basic parts of Music Theory and
bass plane the topic of intervals and
the major scale so what are intervals
well an interval is a measurement or
unit of musical distance just as meters
centimeters miles feet yards and inches
are all measures of physical distance
the smallest unit we use in general
western music is the semitone and that's
really easy to see on a bass guitar neck
because it's just one Frets worth of
distance so if we're on a c third fret
on the a string and we move up one fret
to a c Shar that's one semitone of
distance so C to C Shar is a semitone if
we want to move up a tone that's two
semitones of distance that'll be two
Frets of distance so C to D that's a
turn we can move up and down these two
two so C down to b a fret that's a semi-
tone C down to B flat that's a tone and
it doesn't matter where you play these
or what note the principle still applies
so D to a d Shar is a semit tone D to e
is a tone G Shar to a is a semitone G
Shar to a Shar is a tone and so on now
turns and semi- turns are great for
describing and measuring small units of
distance but to describe something much
larger like let's say a g up to a high V
flat uh would become much much more
difficult in terms of tones and semmit
tones we'd be looking at 20 or more
semmit tones of distance and it's much
harder to measure and keep track of uh
you wouldn't use centimeters or inches
to measure a large physical distance
you'd be more likely to use miles or
kilometers so we need another set of
terms to describe these larger musical
distances and that's where the major
scale comes in major scales are built up
from a formula of tones and semmit tones
uh and that formula is uh tone tone
semmit tone tone tone tone semmit tone
so two tones and a semmit tone and then
three tones and a semmit tone uh that
might sound a little confusing but it'll
make more sense when you see it on the
neck so if we take a c at the third fret
on the a string and then move up a tone
to the D then up a tone to the E then up
a semitone to the F that's the first
part turnone turnone semi tone then we
continue up to the G upper tone up
another tone to the a up another tone to
the B and then finally up a semitone to
the C that's the whole formula tone tone
semmit tone tone tone tone semit tone so
that gives us all these notes c d e f g
a b c and that's the c major scale now
it's all well and good no in the scale
on one string but to be of more use to
us we really need to learn these notes
across the strings so if we start on the
C third fret on the a string with the
second finger and work across we end it
with the c then D fifth fret on the a
string with the fourth finger e second
fret on the D string with the first
finger F third fret on the D string with
the second finger G fifth fret on the D
string with the fourth finger
a second fret on the G string with the
first finger B fourth fret on the G
string with the third finger and finally
C fifth fret on the G string with the
pattern you want to learn it both up and
down uh and make sure you memorize the
pattern really well because uh this is
going to be used over and over and over
playing okay
now the good thing about a bass or a
guitar or any threed instrument is that
these fingering patterns that we're
learning are actually movable now this
is a bit of a shortcut and other
instrumentalists might find this a
little bit of a cheat uh in that you
don't have to learn the individual notes
for a particular scale on a piano for
instance you'd have to learn each scale
by its palet of pitch names and its
combination of white and black keys or
accidentals uh so you'd have to know
that there for instance there's an F in
a g major scale Etc on a guitar or a Bas
you don't really need to do that of
course you're going to need to learn all
that stuff eventually anyway uh but to
begin with uh you can just just to help
with the learning process uh it's worth
learning these patterns so if we look at
the fingering pattern that we've used
for this major scale and have a look at
how we've assigned a certain finger for
each fret we'll find that the first
finger is taking the second fret second
finger is taking the third fret third
finger is taking the fourth fret and the
fourth finger is taking the fifth fret
on each string now if we take that
fingering pattern and we just move it up
a turn so that the second finger is now
on the d uh and then we move that exact
same fingering pattern that we used for
the c major of second finger fourth
finger first finger second finger fourth
finger first finger third finger fourth
finger that's the D major scale you can
move it wherever you want to uh to start
so let's start on a
g that's the G Major scale an a it's the
a major scale C Shar C major scale gsh
t- major scale wherever you want to play
it that pattern and combination of tones
and semi- tones is a major scale so
practice that around the neck starting
on different notes and then you'll be
ready to move on to the intervals that
are within the major scale so to learn
these intervals first we need to number
the notes of the major scale so if we
use the same C major scale as an example
and we number the notes we get the
following first second third fourth
fifth 6th 7eventh and we're back to the
octave and can repeat the pattern again
these numbers are actually referred to
as scale degrees so we can use them to
describe Melodies and baselines with
reference to which notes of the scale or
key are being used so if we go through
them again C is the first degree of the
c major scale uh it's also called the
tonic or root note because it's the home
and starting note that we use to label
the scale D the second degree e the
third f is the fourth degree G is the
fifth degree a is the 6th degree B is
the 7th degree and C is back to the
tonic so you can see that the major
scale is actually classed as a seven
note scale even though when we play up
and down there seem to be eight notes
because we include the octave when we
get to the
top so these scale degrees are the basic
for naming and describing musical
intervals and there's a difference
between scale degrees and intervals and
that'll become more apparent once we've
covered the actual interval names but
for now just go with it so the intervals
within a major scale use the same
numbering system but we add an extra
name to them uh and that can be more
simply described as the first the fourth
and the fifth are all perfect and all
the other are major in a major scale so
the first is actually referred to as the
Unison which sounds a little bit weird
as we're only playing one note at a time
uh but that just comes from the fact
that the study of Harmony uh generally
deals with polyphonic music so if we
play the major scale again with all the
interval names we end up with the
following perfect Unison major 2 major
3D perfect fourth perfect fifth major
6th major 7th and the perfect
octave now we know the intervals within
the major scale scale we can start to
look at them away from a specific scale
or key and more as a measuring stick for
any distance anywhere on the neck at any
time now to do this we need to learn
them all as separate individual patterns
and when you do this you'll start seeing
how everything that we play on bass is
made up of combinations of these
patterns uh this approach to viewing all
the music that you play will have a
profound effect on the speed at which
you learn and it'll form the basis for
pretty much everything that you'll learn
from B basic baselines to Advanced music
theory and I really can't overstate the
usefulness and importance of knowing and
recognizing these intervals all the time
so a straightforward exercise that we
can use to go about memorizing these
intervals is to Simply take a certain
interval and just play it on every fret
from a c up to the 12th fret and back
again so let's take the major third as
an example if we play a major third
pattern on the C the third uh fret on
the a string we have the C and then
we've got the E on the second fret on
the D string and you'll be able to see
that this pattern's like a little
diagonal pattern that moves uper upper
string and down a fret and if we take
time to the 12th
down that's the exercise and we can
apply that to all the other intervals so
if we take
fourth perfect
fifth major
7th Etc as you do this the individual
look of each interval will start to
stand out a little more and you'll begin
to get used to how they're both
different and similar to each other uh
for instance the major 3D looks a little
bit like a major sixth because they both
drop down a fret just on different
strings uh the perfect fifth and the
octave are similar in that exact same
way same fret different string the major
sth that stands out because it's a
little bit different to all the others
uh in just moving up a fret the perfect
fourth that's got its own look of a
barring across the two strings and each
interval needs to be seen to have its
own characteristic look and sound you
want to listen to the sound of each
interval uh and I'll be covering this
oral recognition of the intervals in
another lesson but for now just try to
accept the sounds you hear from each
interval and uh try to hear them before
you play them uh the major second sounds
like the start of a major scale uh
because it is uh the perfect fifth is
used in thousands of baselines and
that's probably the most useful interval
that you'll that you'll learn aside from
the octave and the
Unison and but for now you just need to
concentrate on getting these interval
patterns under your fingers uh and don't
worry about doing too much too soon uh
just try to recognize that there's a
difference to the sound of each of the
intervals as you start playing them and
just pay attention to it now if we get
back to the measuring side of intervals
as we did with semitones and tones at
the beginning of the lesson uh we can
start to see how these new interval
labels can help in describing larger uh
distances so if we take a g on the E
string the third fret and we want to
measure a perfect fifth from it we just
use the perfect fifth interval that
we've learned and we can see that a
perfect fifth from G is D so D is a
perfect fifth from G okay and now if we
take a d on the a string and we see some
pattern involving a c Shar above it we
now know from the intervals that we've
learned that that's a major 7th patter
and that c Shar is a major 7th from D
okay as you learn these interval
patterns by heart you should start to
see these patterns automatically and it
shouldn't be a process of figuring them
out at all uh all the Melodies and Bas
lines that you'll play will start to
appear to you as combinations of these
intervals which in turn could be really
helpful in learning and memorizing
things it's much easier to learn
something when you know that it's just a
succession of building blocks that
you've already learned uh as opposed to
a long string of unrelated notes uh that
can turn into a memory feet just like
learning pi to 200 decimal places Now
One Last Thing Before I finish uh this
first discussion on intervals and that's
the difference between a melodic and a
harmonic interval uh this is a really
simple concept so don't worry A melodic
interval is an interval played one note
at a time just as we've been doing
throughout the lesson so a harmonic
interval is an interval where both notes
are played at the same same time like a
chord when you think of a harmonic it
cones up images of you know harmonics or
overtones of a string that's not what
this means it's simply the two notes of
an interval played together in harmony
so if we take G to a d there perfect
fifth played together it's a harmonic
interval played separately it's a
melodic interval okay so that's the
intervals within the major scale uh stay
tuned for my next video Lesson when I'll
be covering all the other intervals uh
we use in music that's the minor
intervals the augmented uh and
diminished intervals uh and I'll be
clearing up a few Theory terms that
might confuse you that relate to this
discussion of intervals okay please like
this video and uh remember to check out
the comments below for a downloadable
PDF containing all the information that
we've covered in this lesson um also be
sure to subscribe to my YouTube channel
uh I'll be releasing new video lessons
every week and uh you'll get in updates
informing of all the new stuff uh check
out uh the website www.t talkingbass.net
uh where you can get all the lessons
downloadable content and my regular blog
articles that cover loads more base