welcome back to the motherland
channel in times of uncertainty and
potential crisis many individuals turn
to prepping as a means of ensuring their
survival and well-being of their loved
ones while prepping is a personal choice
a way to take control of One's Own
preparedness there have been concerns
about the role of government agencies in
such
scenarios in this video we'll explore
the topic of FEMA the Federal Emergency
Man management agency and the potential
confiscation of prepping items when
shtf it's important to approach this
subject with critical thinking and an
open mind the intention is not to spread
fear or paranoia but to be prepared for
only focusing on prepping here the list
of items we'll discuss is not based on
any official statement from FEMA but it
is a real concern so how concerned
should we all be FEMA's power to confid
skate
stuff within the United States a
comprehensive collection of executive
orders has been established over the
course of several decades these orders
serve to empower FEMA with extensive
executive Authority in the event of a
national emergency or crisis one notable
executive order is eo1 12148 signed by
President Carter according to this order
the director of Federal Emergency
Management assumes the responsibility of
representing the president in
coordinating with state and local
governments as well as the private
sector their primary objective is to
Foster active participation and civil
emergency preparedness mitigation
response and recovery programs by
actively engaging various stakeholders
femma aims to enhance the nation's
ability to effectively address
emergencies and Safeguard the well-being
of its
citizens another significant executive
order is EO
10998 which was issued during President
Kennedy's
Administration this order provides
specific definitions related to
emergency measures in the context of
this order food resources Encompass a
broad range of Commodities and products
that are suitable for consumption by
humans and animals it includes not only
basic food items but also substances
such as starches sugars vegetable and
animal fats and oils cotton tobacco wool
mohare hemp flax fiber and Naval storage
however it's important to know that once
these materials seiz to be recognized as
agricultural Commodities or products
they no longer fall under the scope of
food resources EO 10998 defines farm
equipment as Machinery equipment and
repair parts primarily intended for use
in agricultural activities associated
with the production or Preparation of
food
resources Additionally the order
clarifies that fertilizer refers to any
product or combination of products
specifically designed for plant
nutrition and distributed to
users lastly food resource facilities
Encompass the infrastructure including
plants Machinery Vehicles including
those used on farms and other related
facilities involved in the production
processing distribution and storage
including cold storage of food
resources furthermore these facilities
also handle domestic distribution of
farm equipment and fertilizer another
executive order is EO
10995 which provides fima with the
authority to assume control over all
Communications and media platforms
during
emergencies this includes the ability to
regulate and direct the dissemination of
information to ensure an organized and
coordinated response to the crisis and
finally there's executive order
10997 which grants FEMA the power to
take control of fuel and various forms
of power this Authority enables FEMA to
coordinate and manage the allocation and
distribution of fuel resources as well
as exercise control over different
energy sources in order to effectively
address emergency
situations so now that we know that fem
has the power to confiscate stuff what
generators generator serve as invaluable
assets during times of Crisis providing
a source of power when traditional
electrical infrastructure is compromised
however it's essential to recognize that
their operation can attract attention
including that of FEMA particularly in
light of the powers granted to the
agency under EO
10997 as per the executive order FEMA
holds Federal authority to requisition
various forms of fuel and power
necessary to fulfill their their mission
in emergency
situations this encompassing power
extends to generators which FEMA could
potentially identify based on their
noise or other detection methods even
from a significant distance during
disasters FEMA is known to establish
camps to accommodate affected
individuals and facilitate response
operations it is conceivable that these
camps may require a reliable power
supply for various purposes such as
providing energy for critical
infrastructure medical facilities and
communication systems consequently thema
May exercise their authority to Seas
power sources including generators to
fulfill these
needs
fuel in times of Crisis the availability
of fuel becomes a crucial factor in
determining one's ability to navigate
and respond effectively whether it's
gasoline diesel or other types of fuel
its significance can not be overstated
when a disaster strikes and you bring
fuel into an affected area it becomes a
finite resource upon which you rely
power's essential equipment vehicles and
generators enabling you to sustain
yourself and meet your basic needs
however once your fuel reserves are
depleted you are left with limited
options either Evacuate the area or
search for additional fuel sources
during such circumstances FEMA empowered
by various executive orders May May
develop an interest in your fuel
stockpile given their Authority they
possess the ability to requisition fuel
to support their operations particularly
when it comes to fueling their vehicles
providing energy for critical
infrastructure and facilitating
emergency response efforts this means
that your fuel reserves painstakingly
accumulated for emergency situations
could potentially be subject to
confiscation
weapons
while there are limited precedents for
such actions instances of weapons being
seized have occurred in specific
circumstances such as in New Orleans
after Hurricane Katrina and in Boston
following the Marathon bombing these
incidences have raise concerns and Spark
debates about the balance between
individual rights and Public Safety in
the event of a major crisis FEMA as a
federal agency task with emergency
response may face the challenging task
of maintaining order and ensuring Public
Safety it's possible that they may seek
to disarm individuals and collect
Firearms aiming to prevent potential
misuse or acts of violence during the
emergency response and Recovery phase
the issue becomes complex when
considering constitutional rights
particularly the protections provided by
the Second Amendment but in the face of
an emergency FEMA might argue that the
temporary suspension or restriction of
certain rights including the Second
Amendment
is necessary for the greater public good
and the effective management of the
crisis radios and communication
devices as previously established FEMA
has legal backing for confiscating
communication devices the
conspicuousness of a large antenna on
your truck May attract FEMA's attention
the magnitude of the disaster often
correlates with FEMA's increased need or
desire for additional resources they
would highly value reliable
communication tools like Bal Fang radios
or powerful ham systems to augment their
communication operations considering the
potential confiscation of such items it
becomes pertinent to review the storage
methods for ham radios and evaluate
whether it's necessary to adopt more
covert means of utilizing and
safeguarding
them medical
supplies FEMA will take measures to
procure medical equipment and medicines
confiscating items they deem essential
from your medical stockpiles medical
supplies are even more vulnerable than
food because if FEMA determines you to
be healthy they may consider your
medical preps unnecessary and seize them
well they must leave you some food to
sustain yourself they may approach
medical supplies
differently
food as mentioned earlier fuma possesses
the authority and intent to not only
take away food but also take control of
farms once they acquire food resources
they determine how the distribution will
occur imagining all your store food
being taken away in an emergency is
distressing particularly after years of
preparation people who are unconcerned
about you and your family may be the
ones taking your Provisions thus it
becomes crucial to maximize the
utilization of multiple hidden storage
locations if our genuine intention is to
help during a crisis we may need to
relinquish a portion of our visible food
storage to FEMA while secretly
preserving the majority of our stockpile
in hidden
locations bottled
water water is an indispensable resource
in any disastrous scenario having a
sufficient supply of bottled water is
critical it's recommended to store at
least one gallon of water per person per
day for a minimum of 3 days counting for
both drinking and sanitation
needs additionally understanding water
filtration methods is crucial in some
situations stored water may become
depleted requiring the utilization of
alternative water sources learning about
various filtration techniques such as
using water filters or purification
tablets can help ensure the safety of
water collected from natural sources
like rainfall rivers or
lakes it's essential to familiarize
yourself with proper filtration
procedures to minimize the risk of
waterborne
illnesses during a disaster
contamination of local water sources is
a common occurrence Public Water Systems
may become compromised making the water
in your home the only viable option for
consumption in such situations the
availability of your stored water
becomes
invaluable however it's important to
recognize that FEMA May seize your water
Reserve so keep a portion hidden to
ensure your family's needs are met as
standing in line for a bottle of water
from your own pre purchase case can be
infuriating the void left by the absence
of civil defense civil defense in the
United States was a comprehensive
preparedness plan that was designed by
and for the people it served as a
brilliant framework to ensure the safety
and wellbe of the nation however with
the end of the Cold War American Civil
Defense gradually faded into obscurity
leading to a shift in Focus towards a
sense of Perpetual security and
prosperity solely relyant on a country's
formidable military capabilities
unfortunately the absence of civil
defense is left a void that's been
filled with various responses including
individual prepping panic and divisive
blame within our
nation in the absence of a centralized
civil defense system agencies such as
FEMA and DHS have emerged to ass assum
the responsibility of keeping us safe
from both perceived and actual threats
including the Spectre of natural
disasters and the notion of unseen
enemies the significant powers vested in
FEMA are a consequence of our Collective
abdication of responsibility as American
citizens in our pursuit of immediate
gratification and complacency we've
prioritized entertainment and Leisure
over the imperative of preparedness for
future disasters consequently FEMA and
other emergency response agencies have
been burdened with the arduous task of
compensating for our lack of Readiness
based on personal experiences and
insights shared by fellow Preppers who
have interacted with FEMA it's evident
that the agency's effectiveness is often
questioned while FEMA plays a critical
role in Disaster Response it can never
match the effectiveness of prepared
communities and neighboring communities
that rally together in times of Crisis
and that wraps it up for today if you
found this video helpful share it with
your friends give it a thumbs up and
don't forget to subscribe and click on
the little bell notification too for
more valuable content till next time