my daughter husband and I have been
living in this adorable Tri level for
about 7 years now in Virginia and I will
say that I started out foring this house
as much as possible trying to fill it as
quickly as I could but over the past
four or five years now I have been very
intentionally decluttering it and we are
where we are now I thought we'd do a fun
tour starting right in my living room
talking about what I do own and
hopefully giving you some ideas on how
you can declutter your own what I really
wanted in my living room was to have a
space that felt easy to clean but also
just open and fresh and beautiful so I
love to bring in plants and I have
several around my house that are my
favorites but I also really like the
look of wood so while our hardwood
floors are beautiful in their own I also
wanted to add these wooden shelves which
I know we all have our opinions on them
but I really like them the way they are
one of my favorite things about this
living room is this behind the couch
table not only did my husband make it
himself and so it's exactly what I
wanted Dimension wise but also what I
found is that when it comes to Furniture
pieces the only ones that I bring in now
pieces that I think are functional but
also beautiful the couch that my grandma
gifted me for my birthday a couple years
ago is just what I wanted it's high up
off the ground and so it's easy to clean
under the other great thing about this
room are the big bay windows we are so
lucky to have these massive windows that
bring in tons of natural light so I
never wanted to cover them up with
really heavy curtains when I walk right
in the door I knew that we needed
function so I made sure to put a
keychain holder that also has a place
that we can put our excess mail and then
on the little shelf that is right near
our door I also put a bowl to throw in
things like sunglasses and my headphones
while you're going through your entryway
make sure that you have enough places
for your clutter so things like my
daughter's book bag and my purse I
wanted to be obvious where to put them
and easy to access no home feels
complete to me unless you have a
decluttering basket and that's exactly
what this small basket is right near our
door and as you can see it already has a
bag that's ready to go as we turn and go
into my dining room it's pretty dramatic
I painted it this color back years ago
when we first moved in and I still
really like it on the walls I have a few
of my favorite pieces one of them is
from my grandfather before he passed
away and the other one is this beautiful
Sunburst mirror we are looking for some
new chairs to go in our dining room
because the ones we have were found on
the side of the road and they are not
holding up well but they were free so I
guess we can't complain as you turn into
our kitchen I would love for this
kitchen to be open floor plan right into
the living room but it's one of those
things that it would cost a lot of money
and a lot of hassle so we just Haven got
into it yet but the countertops and the
sink have been replaced and I love our
new cook top that's just extremely
simple for us to clean with a little
soap and water though I don't love our
black refrigerator it is so easy to keep
clean and you don't constantly have to
see fingerprints the kitchen is pretty
simple we unfortunately don't have any
kind of pantry and so the little
cabinets on the side do hold all of our
food which which in turn actually is
probably helpful because there is no
place for our food to go hide and we
forget to eat it everything is right
there in the open in these little
baskets that I've put and labeled so
it's easy to know when we need to go to
the grocery store again before we leave
this floor I wanted to show you my
entryway closet now there's not a lot of
Pizzaz going on in this closet it's
extremely functional there's a little
bench that we can sit on to put our
shoes on when necessary and underneath
the bench I have three small shoe
containers one for me one for my
daughter and one for my husband I love
these containers cuz they're so easy to
clean and they're actually the perfect
size Keeps Us in check and so we're not
just over buying shoes just because and
then my husband took out the rod that
had hangers because the hangers just got
very frustrating trying to keep our
coats on them and not have them fall off
so instead we opted for some hooks that
I think are very beautiful but also
extremely functional again then looking
up we have two more baskets one of them
holds most of the things for our outdoor
activities we also have a few games we
keep in here for easy access and then
the other basket is great for just our
hats and gloves let's go ahead and
travel downstairs as you can see it's
basically just one big sitting room that
we also use as our office our office is
usually semi cluttered throughout the
day just from me working at it all day
and my husband at night have a TV down
here this is where we'll do movie nights
or game nights and then onto the side we
have a small bathroom that my husband
couple years ago updated which is
beautiful town here used to be a really
ugly Brown bathroom that was just all
different shades of brown so I'm so
grateful that he was able to get this
done and then finally on the side you
can see this is just a utility room my
husband's tools are often in here and
then things like the laundry also are
down here I will say the best thing we
put in this laundry room is just this
very simple shelf it's amazing what
having a little bit of storage does in a
space that used to feel so cluttered as
we head back up the stairs you'll see
that our top floor we have three
bedrooms and one more bathroom this
bathroom is obviously dated and it is
from the 1960s but I actually really
like the tile it is this happy blue
turquoisey kind of color so we haven't
done anything with it but the bathtub
and the sink I would love to replace at
some point down the road because this
bathroom and the closet that's attached
to it is pretty small we need to keep
keep things very simple so in the
bathroom closet I have several different
homes that I keep for things like
medicine and our towels and rags and
while I used to feel like every linen
closet had to be full to the brim in
order to be a well-run house I have
found that having a few rags and one
towel each a few extra just for my
daughter and the dogs is all I really
need we don't have a medicine cabinet up
here so instead we do have another
little white container that we use as
has our medicine cabinet and it works
great inside of the basket what I will
say to do is get a bigger basket and
then get smaller baskets inside to hold
your smaller stuff so everything isn't
just roaming around all the time it's
like you're creating a drawer even
though you don't have one if you go
right under our sink you'll see that we
have some more storage down there where
is basically I just keep our cleaning
supplies and our small trash can so that
the dogs don't get into it and then just
a few extra things like perfume and
lotions that we use throughout the week
in the two drawers on the side one of
them is dedicated for my stuff like my
makeup but also our toothbrushes we put
them inside of the drawer just so that
the countertop can stay very visually
clear and then the other drawer is
dedicated just for my husband's
stuff then if we head back out you'll
see my daughter's room is the first one
we come to because my brother recently
moved out we were able to take all of
her toys back out of her room room and I
will show you where we put them now but
in her room it's very simple we have a
few pieces of artwork up that she's done
or my nieces have done and then we have
some simple shelves for books and then
in her closet we will store some clothes
for The Following season but I try not
to keep too much create a home for those
kind of items and don't explode out of
them know that this is all you are able
to keep if it fits in that spot as far
as keepsakes I have for Ken I have one
small container that I keep for
everything from0 to 4 years old and then
now I have something that I keep for all
of her school years it's in a kind of
binder that I actually think I just got
from Michael's the next room next to my
daughter's is our room and like I said
with my daughter's room as well I like
to keep things very simple when it's a
place that you sleep the simpler it is
the easier it is for me to fall asleep
to stay asleep and if I do happen to
wake up to go back to sleep very easily
when I had a lot of decor around a lot
of knickknacks around a lot of pictures
around and TVs I had a really hard time
falling asleep quickly or being easily
distracted by those things that I saw so
if you are like me and you're having a
hard time falling asleep staying asleep
then simplifying your room as much as
possible it's going to help you to fall
asleep a lot easier as you can see I
actually don't have any Decor up at all
besides this one beautiful mirror that
my husband actually built the casing on
the outside besides that I like to just
have a plant and keep it very simple I
don't want to have to be thinking about
what I need to clean in the morning
while I'm trying to sleep in our closet
we've redone this Closet in particular I
used to just have one long bar for
everything in the middle and I just
found that it wasn't functioning the way
that we needed to and so what we did is
we just got a big piece of wood my
husband cut it down we got more brackets
from Amazon and they've done an amazing
job just having some extra shelves
didn't want to have to have a dresser
anymore because this is a smaller size
room not tiny but smaller and the
dresser we had just took up so much
space and I found that I was always
having to dust it then you can see on
either side we actually have two bars
each which is actually more storage than
we even need and another thing that I
definitely suggest that we do as well in
our closet is to have all matching
hangers I just find that no it isn't
necessary but I do feel like having all
of the same hangers does make the closet
look look instantly more appealing then
finally in the last room in our house we
have this playroom SL office area that
my daughter often does her crafts in and
while it is extremely simple I feel like
there is definitely a beauty to this
room it's amazing to me that while I
used to think Simplicity of Decor was a
turn off now that I find the Simplicity
to be so
refreshing in the closet I have created
some storage just from what we happen to
have around the house and that's where
now we have labeled her toys and some of
our extra coats in that closet because
it is Spring right now where I live and
so I didn't want to have the coat
clutter
downstairs if you have enjoyed this
little tour of my house then please
remember to subscribe and of course if
you are on a decluttering journey as
well throw a heart emoji down below to
let us know that we are all in this