we've got the three v's here of
communications we have the verbal
the verbal is the content of the message
itself they're the words that you're
we have the vocal the vocal is the sound
the tone the pitch the projection of
your voice what people hear of you
and then finally we have the visual what
people see
of the way that you come across so if
you were to take a look at these
and say well i think what do i think
counts in communicating
so go ahead and in your own mind just
prioritize these
what do you think is more heavily
weighted over the others
let's just take a show of hands here how
many people think that
verbal is most or equal importance
the words that you say most are equal
got a few hands there all right vocal
most are equal
visual most are equal hey we got a smart
group you're not sleeping that's that's
great
all right well let's take a look at the
numbers and see what they say this is a
classic study done by professor albert
morabian
out of ucla but before i show you those
numbers let me have you do a quick
exercise
make an okay sign with your right hand
everybody do this without hitting your
your neighbor hold it out in front of
you
everyone see it out in front of you
above your head
everyone above your head out to the side
and put it on your chin
yeah on your chin let's see
all right they're still gone it's on my
chin what on your
chin oh fine uh
yeah oh that's the chin that's my chin
right here what's most important
the visual now let me show you these
but let me first tell you what this does
not mean again this is the classic study
professor albert moravian he wrote a
book called
silent messages the numbers that he
found in his research certainly reflect
that title take a look
now let me tell you what this does not
mean
this does not mean that the words you're
saying that the content the meat of your
presentation
only accounts for seven percent of your
experience
what it does mean though is that when
the message
is inconsistent that is when the words
that you're saying
don't match what people see or what they
hear
as you're saying it they believe what
they see
over the actual word it's as if i didn't
even say
chin i had 80 of the audience going this
is my
you've got to have a consistent
message to engender this trust and
believability that your listener has
in you and in your message you have to
think about getting